All right, welcome to the grand finale of
dynamic programming in 6 .006, four of
four. Today we are going to focus in on a
particular type of subproblem that we saw
at the very beginning with Fibonacci, which
is when you have an integer input. And a
natural thing to do with that integer
input is look at smaller versions of that
integer. And this is going to lead us to a
new notion called pseudopolynomial time.
We've talked a lot in this class about
polynomial time being a good running time.
But pseudopolynomial is a pretty good
running time. And we'll talk about that.
And it relates to these integers. We'll
only look at two new examples, rod cutting
and subset sum. But then we're going to
review all the examples we've seen from a
kind of diagonal perspective. So as usual,
we're applying our sort bot framework with
subproblems, relations, topological order,
base cases, original problem, and time.
Quick review.
So the hardest part is getting the right
set of subproblems. And there are some
natural choices for sequences. We
try prefixes, suffixes, substrings. For
integers, like in Fibonacci, there's a
given number n. You want to compute that at
the nth Fibonacci number. What we ended up
doing was solving Fibonacci numbers for all
input numbers, input integers between 0 and
that number n, or in this case, capital K.
And that's a general technique. And
we'll see two more examples of that today.
Otherwise, we take products of these.
And often, that's enough. But sometimes, we
need to add more subproblems in what we
call subproblem expansion, often with extra
constraints that let us remember some state
about the past. My canonical example of
that is the piano fingering, where we had
to remember what our fingering assignment
was, in some sense, from the previous step
in order to compute the transition cost.
And this is a very powerful technique.
You can also use it to play Super Mario
Brothers optimally if you have a constant
size screen. And all you need to remember
is what's in the constant size screen. If
everything outside that screen resets, you
can just add that state as a parameter
to your subproblem. And you'll be able to
solve Super Mario Brothers.
Anyway, very useful. And that was sort
of the focus of last lecture. We won't talk
about it much here today. And then we
relate these subproblems recursively. And
this is basically the test of whether your
subproblem definition was correct, is can
you write down a recurrence relation, which
is just a recursive algorithm. And there's
a nice general procedure for how to come
up with these relations, which is to just
think up some question about the subproblem
solution that if you knew the answer,
reduced to smaller subproblems. And
then you just locally brute force all the
answers to that question, which I like to
think of as guessing the answer correctly
and then just directly calling the
recursive things. But then at the end, you
have to pay for that guess by looping over
all possible guesses in order to guarantee
that you actually
find the right one.
So once you identify this question, it's
very easy. DP is all about just brute force
anything you want. And usually, that leads
to a pretty good running time as long as
the number of possible answers to that
question is polynomial. Then we need to
check this relation is acyclic. And then
it often reduces to finding a path, like a
shortest path or something in a DAG, the
subproblem DAG. We need some base cases. We
need to make sure we can solve the original
problem using one or more subproblems. And
then we analyze the running time as usually
a number of subproblems times the amount
of non -recursive work in the relation plus
however much time it took us to solve the
original problem. So that was our
framework. We've seen it four times now.
Slightly refined each time. We've
mostly added some general techniques for
subproblem definition
and how to write relations.
So let's do a new example,
which is rod cutting.
This will be pretty straightforward,
but it will serve as a contrast to the next
example we talk about, subset sum. So what
is the problem? The name rod coming comes
from the book CLRS. But it's actually a
pretty practical problem, maybe not for
cutting rods. But you could imagine
you have some resource of a given length. I
like to think, because I have been hardwood
shelf shopping recently, I like to think
of you have a big plank of hardwood.
You could have a sum price for selling that
length. But you could also cut that plank
into multiple pieces of various lengths
that sum to L. And you could sell them
individually. Maybe you make more money
that way. And that's what this problem
is all about. So you're given the value of
every possible length you could cut. We're
going to assume all lengths have to be
integers. Scale
so that that's true.
And we want to know what is the best way
to split up our big rod of length capital L
into various rods of small l length,
potentially different lengths. So I'll call
this the max value partition. In
mathematics, this is called partition, a
bunch of numbers that
sum to a given number.
And
we want to maximize the total value,
naturally. So here's an example. Let's say
our original length is
7. And we have this table
for lengths 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. All the
different lengths. I'm going to write down
a value that's an integer for cutting off
a rod of that length and selling it. It's
like the sell price.
It's presumably monotonic, but it doesn't
have to be. Maybe people really like buying
powers of 2 length or something. And so
those sell higher. So this doesn't have to
be monotonic. But in this example, it is.
And so I have this rod of length 7. And I
could sell it directly for $32, let's
say. But I could also split it into, say, a
length 1 rod and a length 6, or a length 1
rod and two length 3s, or a length 3 and a
4, anything that sums to 7. And probably
the most natural thing to do for this
problem as a heuristic, this would be a
greedy bang for buck heuristic is what it's
usually called, is to take the ratio, how
much money do I get for a given length,
divide V of L by L, and try to maximize
that. That would be, if I had to pick a
single item and sell many of that type,
that would be the optimal thing to do. So
this has a ratio of 1. That's bad. This has
a ratio of 5. That's better. And you stare
at it long enough, I believe 6 is the best,
has the highest ratio. Slightly more than,
I can't divide.
Slightly better than, let's see. Slightly
worse than 4. Slightly worse than 4. Or is
4 the best?
Slightly worse than 4? What do you mean?
31 over 6 is slightly less than 4. Oh,
slightly. I see. The ratio is slightly less
than 4. Thank you. Yeah. Which all of
these others are somewhat worse. For
example, if I double the 3 value, I get 26,
which is quite a
bit less than 31.
And I guess the closest competitor, I
think, is 2. Because if you multiply this
by 3, you get 30. So if I sold three 2's, I
get $30. But if I sell one 6, which is the
same quantity, I get $31. So slight
improvement. And so this item maximizes
bang for buck, that ratio. And so one
natural partition is 6 plus 1. I sell one
rod of length 6, and that leaves a rod of
length 1. And this will give me 31 for the
6 and $1, which gives me $32. But
this turns out to not be the best, which is
actually the same as if you just sold it
outright. But in fact, you can do better by
selling. This is not obvious. Stare at it
for a while. A 3 and a 4 also sums to 7.
Then we get 13 plus 18, which is hopefully
bigger. 33. 30. Get this right. Nope, I did
not get it right.
That's too small. We're going to take these
two and sell 3 plus 2 plus 2. Then I get
13 plus 10 plus 10. Remember, 2 was a close
competitor for the ratio for 6. So it's a
little better to sell two 2's and then a 3,
because then we get $33. And that turns
out to be the best for this problem. And it
seems really tricky to figure this out. In
general, there are exponentially many
different partitions. Can't afford to try
them all. Question? Can I have negative
values? Can I have negative values in here?
I think that will work fine. I'm not
allowed to have negative lengths or 0
lengths. I don't want 0 lengths to actually
give you something, because then I just
cut infinitely many 0's. But the V of L, I
think, could be negative. Do I have to use
the whole bar?
Sorry. In this problem, yes. I think it
wouldn't change much if you didn't have to
use the whole bar. We can think about those
after we write the DP. So let's solve this
with sort bot.
So what's the input to this problem?
Well, we have, I didn't mention this is an
integer length.
Positive integer length.
So we have one input, which is an integer
L. And we have another input, which is, I
guess, it's like an array of integers. So
this is a sequence. And this is an integer.
So if we look at our list of nice
subproblems, we could try prefixes or
suffixes or substrings of the value
structure. Or we could try for that integer
smaller integers. And that's actually what
I prefer. I think the way to think about
this is to jump ahead to what do we want
to, what feature of the solution do we want
to guess? And presumably, we should think
about what is some length of rod that we
will cut and sell. This big rod, maybe I
sell the whole thing. Maybe I cut off a
thing of size 1 and sell it. Maybe I cut
off a thing of size 2 and sell it. But I
have to sell something, unless I'm not
selling anything. And so there's only L
different choices for what rod lengths
to cut off first. And so we can just brute
force that in order L time. So what problem
do we get if we cut off an integer of some
small l length? Well, we just get the
same problem with a rod of length capital L
minus small l. The values don't change. It
happens that I won't use the big values if
I cut off some amount of the problem. But
I like to think of this as we're just, all
we're doing is decreasing big L. And so my
subproblems are going to be for each small
l less than or equal to big L, solve that
problem. So x of L is max value partition
of length L, little l, for little l equals
0, 1, up to big L. So just the same
problem, but with different choices
for big L. So this is using this integer
subproblem. This example that happens
to correspond to prefixes of the V array,
because if I only have length up to little
l, then I really only need the prefix of
the value array up to little l. So you
could think of it that way. That's also
fine. But I think this way is
a little more generalizable.
OK. So I claim this is a good set of
subproblems because I can write a
recurrence relation, which
is actually pretty simple.
Like I said,
we want to choose
some piece. So we're given a rod of length
little l. I want to choose how much of that
rod to sell in the next piece. So I could
cut off something of length 1, or I could
sell the whole thing, or cut off any piece
size in between. And the money I will get
for that is whatever the value of that
piece is, plus recursively the maximum I
can get from all the remaining pieces.
Sorry, from the remaining length, which is
little l minus p.
OK. So very simple inside the formula,
just the value for the first piece. We're
guessing what is the first piece we'll
cut off and sell. We get the value for that
piece. And then recursively, we see what's
the best we can do with the remainder. Now,
we don't know what size the first piece
should be. So we reverse it. We try all
possible choices for p and take the max
that we get out of this formula over that
choice. And that's guaranteed
to find the best overall
because we must cut off some piece. Now, if
you wanted to allow not selling anything,
in the case of negative numbers, you could
just add a 0 to this max. And then you
might stop early if there's
nothing left that's worth selling.
OK. Topological order is very simple.
We just have these capital L different
problems. And if you look at, oh, yeah. So
we're looking at l minus p. p is always at
least 1. So we're always strictly
decreasing l in this recursive call. And so
as long as I solve the problems in order
of increasing little l, I'll guarantee that
whenever I'm solving x of little l, I'll
have already solved all the things I need
to call. So if you're writing a bottom
-up DP, this would just be the for loop l
equals 0 up to
big L in that order.
This is equivalent to statement. But
the key is to check that this is acyclic
because we're always referring to
smaller l. And so increasing l is a valid
topological order in this. Subproblem
DAG defined here. There's an edge from an
earlier thing to evaluate
to a later thing to evaluate.
OK. Base case would be x of 0.
That's the first thing we'll want to
compute here. And indeed, this formula
doesn't make much sense if I have x of 0
because I can't choose a number p between 1
and 0, even non -strictly. And so what does
it mean? Well, if I have a rod of length
0, I can't get any money
out of it. So that's it. It's just 0.
That's an assumption, but a reasonable
assumption. You don't get something for
nothing. OK. Then we have the original
problem, which is just the length l rod.
And then the time to compute this thing.
How many subproblems are there? Capital L
plus 1. So we'll say
theta l subproblems.
And we'll multiply by the amount of time to
evaluate this max, just a constant number
of things in here, not counting the
recursive call. And so it takes little l
time. Little l is certainly at most big L.
And so we'll say big O of big L time. It's
actually a triangular number, but it will
only affect things by a constant factor. So
we get l squared time.
And we're done. So very simple,
straightforward DP. At this point, we've
seen much more complicated examples than
this. But it highlights a question, which
is, is theta l squared
polynomial time?
So is this a reasonable running time?
And I claim the answer is yes. This is a
reasonable polynomial running time.
You might say, well, of course it's a
polynomial. Look, this is a polynomial, l
squared. That's a quadratic polynomial. But
it's a quadratic polynomial in l. And we
haven't really thought about this too hard.
But what does it mean to be polynomial
time? And this is a notion that's properly
called strongly polynomial time. We won't
worry about that strongly too much in this
class. But if you look this up online,
you'll see the difference. Polynomial time
means that the running
time is polynomial
in the size of the input.
And the size of the input is, for
our model, measured in words,
machine words. Remember our good old word
RAM, w -bit words? It's been very useful
because it lets us assume things like
adding two numbers constant time, as long
as these numbers fit in a word, as long as
they're at most w bits. And generally, we
assume all the things we're manipulating
fit in a machine word because that's the
case where we normally work.
And so the natural way to measure the
size of an input, so in this example, this
problem, rod cutting, the input is a single
number l and this value array V of l,
which is capital L numbers. So I would say
integers. And we've generally assumed, I
didn't mention
integer value here,
as in throughout this class, we assume
that all the integers, unless otherwise
specified, fit in a word. So we've got one
word here and l words here. So the total
size of the input to this problem is l plus
1 integers. And this problem input size
is l plus 1, which we can think of as just
l, I mean, state of l. OK, so I explicitly
didn't want to use n in this problem
because usually we use the letter n for the
problem size, not quite always. But input
size always means input size. And so here
we can compute it in terms of this
specification. It involves l plus 1 word
inputs. And so polynomial time should be
polynomial in that input size, in l plus 1
in our example. So of course, l
squared is polynomial in l plus 1. So good.
OK, the next example I'm going to show
is going to be very similar, but the answer
will be no. Make it more interesting.
But it'll still seem pretty reasonable. So
we'll come back to that issue in a moment.
Let me first show you what the subproblem
DP looks like for this problem. Again, it
took me a while to draw, so please admire.
So this is the same example of these
values, 1, 10, 13, 18, 20, 30, 1, 32, drawn
here on a graph. It's the complete graph
oriented in this increasing way. I think
this is called a tournament in graph
theory. So we have the base case over here.
This corresponds to a length 0 rod where
we get no money. And over here, we have our
full rod of length 7. And I claim the best
that we can do is 33. And what's happening
here is for every value, like 3, that I
could sell a rod of length 3 for $13,
there's an edge that goes from each vertex
to one 3 higher. And those all have a
weight of 13 on them.
And then what we're essentially trying
to do is find a longest path from here to
here, longest because we want to maximize
the sum of values that we get. And we know
if we negate all the weights, that's the
shortest path problem. So we could solve
that with shortest paths in a DAG. But I've
drawn here the shortest path tree from the
base case. So it actually tells us that if
we had a rod of length 7, the best thing to
do is to sell it directly for 31. The bold
lines here are the shortest path tree, or
the longest path tree, I guess. And if we
had something of length 10, we should sell
it directly. If we have something of length
20, we should sell one thing of length 2
and another thing of length 4.
Then we should sell one thing of length
2 and one of length 2. We get 2 times 10
points. And for the 33 case, we sell one
thing of length 2, one thing of length 2,
and then one thing of length 3 is optimal.
So you can read lots of information from
this. And if you write down the DP code,
this is effectively what it's computing
from left to right.
OK. Let's move on to our second
problem of the day. Which is subset sum.
So here we are
given, say, a multi -set.
Multi -set means that I can repeat numbers.
So this is just a sequence of numbers. But
I'd like to use set notation because I want
to use subsets, because it's subset sum.
So this is of n integers.
For rod cutting, we also had to split up
our number L into different values that
summed to capital L. So capital T here is
playing the role of capital L. But before,
we were allowed to cut into any lengths.
And so it was easy. In particular, L sums
to L. Here, presumably, T is not in
this multi -set. And we need to find a
combination of numbers here that add
up exactly to T. Sometimes that's possible.
Sometimes it's not. We're only allowed
to use each number once. But we're only
allowed to use it as many times as it
appears in the subset. OK. So here's an
example. Say A equals 2, 5, 7, 8, 9. And
two examples are T equals 21 and T equals
25 for that same set. So can I get 21 out
of these? Sick. That's hard. I think, let's
see. If I add 7 and 8, I get 15.
Not quite what I want. Cheat. Look
at my answer. Yeah, close. 5, 7, 9.
So this is a yes answer to the question,
does there exist any subset? Because 5, 7,
and 9 sum to exactly 21. And T equals 25, I
don't know a good way to prove to you that
there's no way to write 25 with these
numbers other than I wrote a program that
tried all subsets. Or you could write a
program that runs the DP that we're about
to give. And I'll put no. There's no
succinct way, as far as we know, to prove
to someone that the answer is no for a
given target sum. There is a nice, succinct
way to prove the answer is yes. I just give
you a subset. We'll talk more about that
next lecture.
But these are some examples of the question
you might ask and the answer that we're
looking for. This is what we call a
decision problem. In its original form,
we're just interested
in a yes or no answer.
It's a single bit.
Of course, in the yes case, we might
actually want to find the set. And we can
do that, as usual, with parent pointers,
just like in the bold lines over here.
We'll get to that in a moment. But this
is a little bit different from most of the
problems we've been seeing with dynamic
programming or optimization problems. And
we're trying to minimize or maximize
something. And so we always put a min or a
max on the outside in the relation. Here,
we're going to have to do something that
involves Boolean values,
yes or no, true or false.
And let's solve it. This is actually also
going to be pretty straightforward, in that
we can just use our standard sets of
subproblems. So just like the previous
problem, we have, on the one hand, a
sequence of integers. And on the other
hand, we're given a single integer t.
And what turns out to be right is to use
prefixes or suffixes on this sequence.
And integers less than or equal to t. Let's
think about why.
So that was sort bot for rod cutting.
This is sort bot for subset sum. Again,
I'll look ahead to what feature of the
solution should I guess. Well, I have these
n numbers. Each of them could be in my
subset or not. So I have this binary choice
for each ai. Is it in s or not?
That's a lot of questions to answer. I
can't answer them all at once. But I could
just start with the first one and say,
well, is a0 in s? Yes or no? There's two
answers, locally brute force. If I do that,
what happens to my problem? What new
subproblems do I run into? What do I want
to recurse on? Well, I've eliminated a0.
That will leave a suffix of the ai's. So
suffixes on capital A seem like a good
idea. And what about my target sum? Well,
it depends. If I put a0 in my set s, then
the target sum for the remainder is t minus
a0. So t went down. And so I need in my
subproblems to represent smaller target
sums also. So this is how you figure out
what subproblems you should use. I
mean, you could just try prefixes on this,
suffixes on this, substrings on this. And
yes or no, do I include smaller versions of
t here? But you can also just think about,
try to write a recurrence relation first.
See what things you are naturally recursing
on. Simulate the subproblems that way. So
that's what I like to do.
So I'm going to have a subproblem for
each suffix. So that's x of i. And for each
target sum, and I use these capital letters
for the actual target sum so that I can
use lowercase letters for smaller versions
of them. So this is going to be, does any
subset,
remember, don't first, most important thing
is to define what your subproblems are.
Don't just say, it's the same problem, but
where I replace blah with blah. It can be
very ambiguous. And so does any subset s of
the suffix a from i onwards sum to little
t?
We're going to have this subproblem. The
other important thing is to say how many
subproblems there are and what your indices
can vary over. So i is going to be between
0 and n. And t is going
to be between 0 and big T.
OK? So number of subproblems is n plus
1 times t plus 1, or theta n times 1. Times
t. Cool. Now I claim I can write a
relation, like I said, by, so we have this
suffix from i onwards in a. And so I'm just
going to, because I'm looking at suffixes,
I want to keep with suffixes. So I
should try to guess what happens to a of i,
because then what will remain is a of i
plus 1 onwards. And a of i can either be in
my subset s or not. So there's two choices.
So x of i t is going to involve two
things. So there's an operator here. And
then I have a set of two items, which is I
could choose to not put a of i in my
subset. In that case, I've eliminated a of
i. And what remains is a of i plus 1
onwards. And I didn't change my target sum.
I haven't put anything in s, so I still
want to achieve the same sum. So this is
the case where a i is not in s. And then
the other case is I put a of i in s. In
that case, again, I've eliminated a of i.
And so what remains to figure out is what
happens to a of i plus 1 onwards. But now
my target sum is different, because I put a
number in my set. And so among these
items, they should sum up to not little t
anymore, but now little t minus what I just
added, which is a i. So then if in this
subproblem I get something that sums to t
minus a i, and then I add a i to that set,
I will get something that sums to exactly
t. And so that's a valid solution to this
problem. And because we have brute forced
all possibilities, there were only two, if
we combine these in the suitable way, then
we will have considered all options. Now,
what do we want here? So this is normally
I'd write max or min. But this is a
decision problem. The output is just yes or
no. So this is a yes or no answer. This is
a yes or no answer. This is a yes or
no answer. And so what I want is or.
In Python, this would be called any. Just
are any of these things true? Because if
there's any way to construct a set that
sums to t, then the answer to this is yes.
Cool. So very simple, actually. Just it's
one of the simplest recurrences. But we're
solving what I think is a really impressive
problem. We're asking, is there any
subset? There are exactly 2 to the n
subsets of a here. And we're in some sense
considering all 2 to the n of them. But
because we split it up into n local choices
that are binary and do them only one
at a time, sort of, this is the local brute
force versus global brute force. Global
brute force would be trial subsets, sum
them, see which ones add up. But we're,
in some sense, collapsing a lot of these
choices and reusing subproblems. That's the
whole point of dynamic programming. We're
looking at, for the rest of the sequence
from i plus 1 onwards, I don't really care
exactly which subset you choose. I only
care what it sums to. And that collapses a
lot of different options in the same thing.
I really just want to know, is there any
way to do it with exactly this sum? So I
don't have to think. I don't need to keep
track. If I said, give me all of the
different subsets that sum to t, that would
be exponential time. But because I'm just
asking a yes or no question, this choice
only takes constant time. And we get to sum
them instead of product them because we're
using memoization. That is the beauty of
dynamic programming and this time analysis
rule that we only have to sum over
subproblems because we only compute each
subproblem once. So without memoization,
this would take exponential time, just like
Fibonacci with memoization magic. I just
think this is beautiful. So even though
this is one of our simpler DPs,
I think it's an impressive one.
OK, topological order. Well, let's just
look at these function calls. So here, we
have to be a little bit careful.
If we write x recursively, we always
increment i. But sometimes we don't
decrement t. Sometimes t doesn't go down.
So if I wrote decreasing t here, that would
be bad because sometimes I call with the
same value of t. And I don't want to get
into, I want to ensure that this has
already been computed when I try to compute
this. So i is the right thing. And
we should say decreasing i. It doesn't
actually matter how we order with respect
to t, just any order that is decreasing i
will be good because these
function calls always increase i.
OK, we need a base case.
Base cases. Let's see. Given this aspect, I
think the natural thing is to have a base
case when my suffix is
empty, which is when i equals n.
So I'm going to have a base of n comma t
for any little t. So we don't have a lot of
control of how t is changing. But this is
easy. So this is saying, if I give you no
numbers, what sums can you represent? The
only sum I can represent is 0. OK, so if
t equals 0, then the answer is yes.
And otherwise, the answer is no.
So that's my base case. And that's enough.
And we needed this base case because if we
wrote x of n comma t, this would try
to call x of n plus 1, which doesn't make
sense. But x of n colon is a natural
suffix, which we only allowed i to go up to
n. And that's the empty suffix. So this is
enough. We need the original problem.
Which is the entire string from 0 onwards
and capital T for little t. That's our
target sum. And
then the running time.
As I said, there are n
times t subproblems,
theta. And the amount of work we spend for
each one that isn't recursion is constant.
We just do a couple subtractions,
additions, do an OR and recursive calls, so
constant time. So n times t is the running
time of this algorithm. Let me show you an
example as a subproblem DAG.
Really helpful to see. These are hard
to draw, but they're easy to read. I think
they're helpful to show what's really going
on in this DP. Remember, every node here
corresponds to a possible subproblem we
could have. The choice is for little t on
the top. The choice is for little i on the
left. So the original problem we care about
is i equals 0, t equals 6. This is the same
example that I showed you before, where we
have three. Oh, no. This is a different
example. Sorry. My new set A is 3, 4, 3, 1.
Four numbers here. My target value is
6. This is definitely possible. I can add 3
and 3. This shows that A doesn't have to be
sorted. We're not assuming anything about
the order of A. And we're allowed duplicate
values. And we see, indeed, there's a y
here for yes, it is possible. And how did I
compute that? Well, I just drew a bunch of
arrows. So there's vertical arrows here,
always going from each problem to the next
one above it, because we have this
dependency xi of t calls x of i plus 1
comma t.
The calls are going in this direction. So
the dependency order is you have to compute
things lower down before
you compute things up here.
And indeed, down here is the base case,
where we write yes for the first problem
and no for all the others, because we
don't have any numbers. We can't represent
anything above 0. And then we have these
blue lines. I just drew them a different
color so they stand out, hopefully. And
they correspond to the numbers here. So our
first choice is, do we include 0, which is
3? So that's only possible if we're trying
to represent a number that's greater than
or equal to 3, which reminds me, I forgot
to write down. In this DP, I need to say
this option is only an option if Ai is less
than or equal to t. I just moved my
comments here. Those are the same. So this
notation means I put this item in
this set that we take an or of only if this
condition holds. Otherwise, I omit it,
because it's not a choice. Why is that
important? Because I don't want to call
x on a negative value of t. We only are
allowed to call x here when t is between
0 and capital T. So that's subtlety, but
important for a correct DP.
And then what's happening in here at each
stage, let's take an interesting one, maybe
this vertex, is we look at each of the
incoming neighbors, and we take the or. So
the incoming neighbor here has a no. The
incoming neighbor here has a yes. And so we
write a yes here, which means that
given just these numbers, 3 and 1, we can
represent the number 3, namely
by taking this edge of length 3
and then just going straight down to a base
case. That's yes. That's representing 0.
So in this case, this example, I didn't
draw the parent pointers here, but they're
in the notes. This yes is possible not from
going this way, but from going this way.
So we take the number 3. Then we go down,
which means we skip the number 4. And then
we go left, which means we take the number
3. And then we go down, which means we skip
the number 1. So we can represent 6 as
3 plus 3. Cool. So subset sum, not only can
we solve the decision problem, but
by following parent pointers in the yes
instances, we can actually find a valid
subset. Question? Can we add in that
condition to the relation? Yeah. Is it
possible to deal with that by spending the
number of base cases? Good question. So
it's a generally useful technique to add if
conditions to the cases to only when they
apply. You can write a lot of DPs that way.
And that's why I wanted to stress it.
You could instead of adding this condition
allow the case that little t is negative.
But you have to think about how negative
would it be. You might say, well, maybe
t between minus big T and plus big T is
enough. I don't
think so. It should be
we're at some value t,
and we subtract some ai.
Compare it to big T. Probably they're less
than or equal to big T, because they're not
useful if they're bigger than big T. So
you could first prune the ai's to guarantee
all the ai's are less than big T. Then
minus big T to big T would work. Otherwise,
it's like minus the maximum ai up to big T
would be enough, I think. Yeah? Does this
restrict to only positive integers in the
input? Ah. I am implicitly assuming here
that all the ai's are positive.
I think you can solve it with negative
numbers, but it's not. And maybe we'll do
it in recitation. It's not a trivial change
to this DP. I've definitely thought about
it before. Yeah. So I should have said
positive integers. Thank you. Cool. All
right. So that's subset sum. But we come
back to this question of, is this a good
algorithm? Is polynomial time? So we
have this running time, n times t. So a new
question is, is n times
big T polynomial?
And the answer is no. Why? Because for this
problem, what is the input size? How many
words of input do I have? Well, I have
these n integers. And then I also have the
target sum. So similar to up above, our
input size is n plus 1. But now the labels
really matter. Before, it was l plus 1. And
our running time was a function of l. Now
our input size is just n plus 1. But our
running time is a function of both n and t.
Not polynomial in input size
n plus 1. You cannot write that n times
capital T is less than or equal to n plus 1
to the 27th power. Because you just don't
know how n and t relate. Maybe t is at most
n. Then we're happy. But maybe it's not.
Maybe t is 2 to the n. Why could it be 2 to
the n?
Because what do we know about capital T? We
assume, implicitly throughout the course,
that t fits in a word. That means it's a w
-bit number. So that means it's at most 2
to the w. And you might think, well, we
know about a relation between w and n. So
we know t is at most
2 to the w, if it's w bits.
We know that our assumption is always that
w is at least log n. That's the word -ram
trans -dichotomous assumption. But notice,
we don't know anything about an upper bound
on w. In order to upper bound t in terms
of n, I'd need to say that w is at most log
n. Then this would be at most n, and we'd
be done. But that's not very interesting.
And generally, we allow w to be arbitrarily
large with respect to log n. It just has
to be at least log n, just
to be able to index stuff.
It could be really big, much bigger than
log n. For example, w equals n is not a
crazy idea. I mean, if I have a machine
that can represent n numbers, why not
represent n numbers, each of which is n
bits long? And maybe it takes a little more
time to compute on those. You might want
to scale your running times. But it's quite
reasonable to think about n -bit numbers.
And then this is like n times 2 to the n.
So this would actually be exponential
time. If w is 2 to the n, n times t is
exponential
in the problem size, which is n plus 1. And
that's just an example. w could be bigger.
So this is not what we call a polynomial
algorithm or strongly polynomial algorithm.
But it's still pretty good. As long as we
know that capital T is not ginormous, then
this is a great algorithm.
And we capture that notion with a
concept called pseudo polynomial.
It's not the best term, but it's the
established term. It's like polynomial, but
not quite. And the definition of this
term, so we have the definition of strongly
polynomial time. Now, pseudo polynomial
time, sorry, time here. You can measure
other things with pseudo
polynomial, is that we're polynomial in
the input size,
just like before,
and the input
numbers, input integers.
OK? So in this problem, the input integers
capital T and a0, a1 up to an minus 1. So
what we want now is a polynomial, or what
some people call a multinomial, where our
variables are all of these integers. And
we want to be polynomial in them. So we're
allowed to take some constant power of
capital T and some constant number of the
ai's. We can't just take the product
of all of them. That would be big.
So it's a, I guess I should say,
constant degree polynomial.
And indeed, this is a, you might call it a
quadratic polynomial in the input size and
one of the numbers. So this running
time is pseudo poly, but not poly.
And so while normally we think a polynomial
time is good, exponential time is bad,
pseudo polynomial is what we
normally call pretty good, to be informal.
Yeah. So in particular, pseudo polynomial
implies polynomial in the special case
if the input integers are
all at most polynomial
in the input size.
This should sound familiar. This is a
constraint we've seen before. This is the
condition when radix sort runs in
linear time. Radix sort runs in linear time
exactly when all the input integers are
polynomially bounded in n, which is the
size of the array, which is the input size.
So same condition is appearing again. So
this is sort of a fundamental setting
to think about. And let's see. So in
particular, other structures
we've seen, like counting sort
and direct access arrays,
are also pseudo polynomial.
Any others?
Fibonacci. Sorry? Radix sort. Yes.
Technically, also radix sort are all,
they're not strongly polynomial, but they
are pseudo polynomial. Here, we thought
about this as a dependence on u, which we
got rid of using hashing. But if you just
use the order u running time for, say,
build, that u is like, are bound on the
input integers. And that's only good when
this is polynomial. In general, it's pseudo
polynomial. Same with counting sort. We had
an order u. Now, we improved this in radix
sort to this running time that
was n times log base n of u
plus n, if you
want to be careful.
Or put a ceiling. Now, this is a running
time that's a little bit better. And this
is usually called weakly polynomial.
Don't want to spend much time on this.
But weakly polynomial is just like pseudo
polynomial. But instead of being polynomial
in the input size and the input integers,
you're polynomial in the log of the
integers.
So this is better. And it's almost as good
as polynomial, as strongly polynomial. We
won't really use this notion. The only
place it appears in this class is in radix
sort. But future classes, you might care
about. So the nesting is the best thing you
can be is strongly polynomial. We just
call this polynomial in this class. Then we
have weakly polynomial, which is almost
as good. But you have this logarithmic
dependence on the numbers. And then the
next level is pseudo polynomial. This is
not as good. Here, this really only works
well if the numbers are small. Logarithmic
dependence is pretty good, because even
if they're exponential, this is polynomial.
Sounds funny. But log of an exponential is
polynomial. All right. Enough about pseudo
poly. The last thing I want to talk
about is reflecting on all of the dynamic
programs we've seen so far and
characterizing them according to the big
techniques that we used in sort of the
first big technique was, how do we define
our subproblems? Did we take prefixes and
suffixes or substrings of a sequence? Did
we have multiple sequences and have to
take products of those spaces? Did we have
integers and have to take smaller versions
of those integers? Sometimes that leads to
pseudo polynomial algorithms, sometimes
not. And sometimes we also had subproblems
that were defined in terms of vertices.
This just happened in shortest path
problems, because that's the only setting
where we saw DP over graphs. Let me
characterize all the DPs we've seen in
lecture, not the recitation ones for now,
in red.
So for example, with the bowling problem,
with bowling pins, we only had to deal with
prefixes or suffixes, because we could just
think about what happened for the first
couple of pins, for example. Also for LCS,
we had to take two different sequences. But
then we just guessed what happened with the
first two items of each sequence. And so
that only left us with suffixes. With
longest increasing subsequence, again, we
just guessed whether the first, or maybe
we assumed that the first item was in the
longest increasing subsequence. And then we
tried to guess what the next item was. But
that, again, eliminated everything in
between. So we were just left with a
suffix. This leads me to another
characterization of the dynamic programming
techniques, which is for, in addition to
these basic subproblems, we often added
constraints and expansion. And LIS is an
example of what we call non -expansive
constraint, where we just added a
constraint to the problem, which was I'd
want this first item to be in my longest
increasing subsequence. But that didn't
actually change the number of subproblems.
So it didn't expand the number of
subproblems. This is, I think, the only
example we saw with this feature. Most of
the other times when we added a
constraint, we also increased the number of
subproblems, which we'll get to.
OK. Also, in a certain sense, there's
multiple ways to think about this. One,
Floyd -Warshall is a problem where we
define subproblems based on prefixes of the
vertices. Vertices 1 through n, we said, is
there a shortest path using vertices just
1 to i? So that's a prefix of the vertex
set in a particular order. So you can think
of Floyd -Warshall as involving a prefix.
You can also think of it as you're given an
integer i, and you're only allowed to use
vertices less than or equal to i. And so
it's also kind of an integer subproblem.
But I will leave it up there. Also, the two
examples we saw today,
rod cutting, kind of.
You could think of it as either a prefix on
the values, or I would prefer to think of
it down here,
where we had an integer and we were
considering smaller integers also. But
subset sum definitely had a suffix. In
addition to having an integer subproblem,
so rod cutting you can put down here
because we looked at smaller integers, or
up here. But subset sum really is up here
and down here, because we both looked at
suffixes and smaller values of t. OK.
Fibonacci also fits down here. Fibonacci
was another case where we had a number n,
and we looked at integers smaller than n.
Good. I think I've done these. Now, what
problems involve substrings? We saw two of
them. One was the alternating coin game,
because we were taking from left or right.
We had substrings in between. And the other
is parenthesization, where we had to guess
something in the middle, and that left the
prefix before it and the suffix after. Both
of those are typical ways where
you get substring problems.
OK. So pseudopoly,
both of these are pseudopoly.
And those are the ones that we've seen that
are dynamic program pseudopoly. And then
with vertices, it's all the shortest path
problems, where we also had a parameter
which was a vertex. These are natural,
because the goal of single shortest paths
is distance to each vertex. And so
naturally, we had a subproblem for each
vertex, for Dagg shortest paths, for
Bellman -Ford, and for Floyd -Warshall. OK.
Back to subproblem expansion, we saw a
couple of examples, alternating coin game
and parenthesization. Sorry, not
parenthesization. Yeah, parenthesization.
Sorry. Arithmetic parenthesization. So
here, we considered two different versions
of each subproblem, one where I go first
and one where you go first. And that was
really handy, though not necessary. For
parenthesization, it turned out we needed
both min and max in order to solve max.
So we really only cared about max, so we
doubled the number of subproblems
to make it solvable. For piano and guitar
fingering, we increased the number of
subproblems by a constant, or f, or some f
to the f. For five fingers, this is a
reasonable constant. For some amount of
state that we wanted to keep track of of
the past. And one example where we had
linear expansion, sort of, is Bellman
-Ford. So here, we were expanding by how
many edges are in the shortest path. So
we really only cared about finding shortest
paths. We said, oh, what about at most i
edges? So you can think of that as adding a
constraint. And then there's n different
variations of these subproblems, which
leads to expansion. You could also think
of it as just adding a single constraint,
which is I care about the number of edges.
And that input is an integer. And then
we're looking at the natural subproblem
for integers, which is we care about up to
length n minus 1. And now let's consider
all lengths smaller than n minus 1. And
finally, the other main feature we had is
in the recurrence relation. And all these
shortest path DAGs, how many incoming edges
did we have? How many different branches
did we have to consider?
Combined in some way. So we saw a
lot of examples with constant branching.
Fibonacci, where we just, there's the
obvious two -way branching. Bolling, where
we had a couple of choices at the
beginning. LCS, longest common subsequence,
where we had a couple of choices what to
do at the beginning. Alternating coin game.
Similarly, do we take from the left
or the right? So just two choices. Floyd
-Warshall, just two choices. Do we use that
vertex or not? Subset sum, do we include
this item in the subset or not? OK. So that
was all constant branching. In a lot of
the graph problems, we got order degree
branching, which leads to an order e term
in the final running time, namely DAG
shortest paths and Bellman -Ford. And then
a lot of examples had linear branching. In
particular, longest increasing subsequence,
where we didn't know what the
next increasing item was. So there are n
possible choices for it. Parenthesization,
where we had to choose anybody in the
middle as the last operator. And rod
cutting that we saw today, we could cut the
first rod we cut
could be any length.
And then finally, once you've considered
all, recursed on all these subproblems, you
have to combine them somehow. And in a lot
of the problems, we actually just take the
one best choice. And that is our final
solution. And in those problems, the final
solution ends up being finding some kind
of shortest path in a DAG. But there are a
few cases where we actually took multiple
solutions and combined them together to get
the overall solution. And this includes
Fibonacci, which is we added them. Not too
interesting. Floyd -Warshall,
we concatenated two paths. And
parenthesization is maybe the most
interesting, where we had to take two
parts, the prefix and the suffix, how to
solve them, and then multiply or add them
together. And so these problems are not
well represented by shortest path in a DAG.
Still a DAG involved, but it's like a
multi -path thing. And then finally, the
original problem often is just a single
subproblem is the original problem. And
there are a few examples, namely DAG
shortest paths and longest increasing
subsequence and Bellman -Ford and Floyd
-Warshall. These were the order that we
covered them. So the three shortest paths
and then longest increasing subsequence,
where here, because we added this
condition, we had to try all the possible
choices for this condition. I think, do we
also have one here today? No. OK. So in
fact, in retrospect, or I mean, we knew
this from the beginning, but for you in
retrospect, these four DP lectures were all
about showing you these main techniques of
dynamic programming, from how to set
up simple subproblems to different types of
basic subproblems to constraining or
expanding those subproblems and having
initially very simple branching and then
getting to bigger branching and different
kinds of combination. We wanted to show you
all these ideas in some order. And if you
look back at the sequence that we covered
problems, we're kind of slowly adding these
different main techniques to DP. And that's
why we chose the examples we did. There
are, of course, many more examples of
DP, very powerful technique. But that's the
end.